<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
      <title>Recent Content on Just another blog with random, unripenend thoughts. </title>
      <generator uri="https://hugo.spf13.com">Hugo</generator>
    <link>http://secretdeveloper.github.io/index.xml/</link>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <author>Gary Kenneally - @SecretDeveloper</author>
    
    <updated>Fri, 14 Oct 2016 12:54:47 UTC</updated>
    
    <item>
      <title>Software, Estimation and the Planning Fallacy</title>
      <link>http://secretdeveloper.github.io/blog/2016/10/14/Software-Estimation-and-the-Planning-Fallacy/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Oct 2016 12:54:47 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Gary Kenneally - @SecretDeveloper</author>
      <guid>http://secretdeveloper.github.io/blog/2016/10/14/Software-Estimation-and-the-Planning-Fallacy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;My flight is delayed for 3 hours so I&amp;rsquo;m taking the rare opportunity to put together some thoughts on how software project estimation can trip companies, teams and individuals up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember way back when we had the Waterfall model?  Well actually we didn&amp;rsquo;t have the Waterfall, the Waterfall model was put forward by Winston Royce back in the early 70&amp;rsquo;s as an example of a &lt;em&gt;broken&lt;/em&gt; SDLC model, unfortunately this little note was lost in the scramble to adopt it as the de-facto model to use!  Lets forget all of that, you would be hard pressed to find any organizations still working under a Waterfall model and the reason for that is pretty strong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It didn&amp;rsquo;t work. A big upfront design session only works if you know what you are designing, anyone who has worked on any Enterprise level applications knows that a project that has a clearly defined end goal is pretty rare. Oh sure there are ideas, and concepts, and even some rules about what it &lt;em&gt;won&amp;rsquo;t&lt;/em&gt; be but often the final product evolves significantly from beginning to end. So if you don&amp;rsquo;t know what you are building until you see it then all of that Waterfall upfront design time is not only wasted effort, it is baggage that you have to carry with you, making it harder to pivot or change plans once the real product starts to form.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;It didn&amp;rsquo;t work so we abandoned it, right? We understand that change and evolution is a part of product development now, right?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;It depends&amp;rdquo; seems to be the answer, we gave up on the structured requirements gathering and big upfront design phases in favour of entering the implementation phases much earlier.  In the Agile world you would look to define an MVP product, Epics are identified and prioritized, you start implementing the pieces you can earlier and find your way as you go.  It&amp;rsquo;s not that this way is the ultimate solution, but at least it works to some degree, where Waterfall did not work at all for most projects (there are projects where large upfront design can work well).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So why are we still expecting upfront estimates considering we know that this is already a flawed model?  And even more puzzling, why do we have an expectation for estimates to be be highly accurate, and for them to get more accurate over time?  Like a hunter stalking deer in a deep forest at night, estimators are expected to get better at hitting the mark with practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lets talk for a moment about why estimation is a broken concept.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Sydney opera house&lt;a href=&#34;#1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt; is one of the most famous budget overruns for any construction project, coming in at a whopping ten years and fourteen times over original estimate, final costs are at around $102M.  But of course that is concrete and steel, surely software doesn&amp;rsquo;t cost as much and is easier to estimate, right?  Not so, Wikipedia keeps a nice list of failed and overbudget software projects&lt;a href=&#34;#2&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;, here are a few highlights:
 - NHS Connecting for Health&lt;a href=&#34;#3&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt; - Estimated at £2.3bn over 3 years, it has so far cost £12.4bn over 10 years.
 - Universal Credit&lt;a href=&#34;#4&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt; - Estimated at £2.2bn this was later revised to £12.8bn and again revised to £15.8bn.
 - Expeditionary Combat Support System &lt;a href=&#34;#5&#34;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt; - $1.1bn was spent with no significant deliverables, another $1.1bn would need to be invested to even achieve a quarter of original scope.
Those are staggering numbers making the Opera house seem like a bargain at $100M.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Software is still a relatively new industry in comparison to construction, each decade sees major changes in how software is built and how projects are managed e.g. Waterfall to Agile. Humans have been building homes and other structures for centuries yet we still fail to accurately estimate the cost of construction. Why are we so bad at estimating?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a number of factors and some previous studies are pretty revealing. &lt;strong&gt;Overly optimistic planning:&lt;/strong&gt; Buehler and associates (1995)&lt;a href=&#34;#6&#34;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt; performed a study on a number of students and asked each of them to estimate the date by which they would be finished their Senior Thesis.  The average was 33.9 days.  They then asked the students to estimate how long it would take if everything went perfectly to plan and the average was 27.4 days.  They then asked how long it would take if everything went as poorly as possible and the response was an average of 48.6 days.  The actual time it took the students to complete their thesis was 55.5 days.  So even when we try to estimate the worst case scenario we fail to come close.  In fact the estimate for how long it will take is very close to the perfect scenario.  It seems people are optimists by nature and while that helps us to believe it is physically possible to build skyscrapers it probably does not help us estimate the cost of the skyscraper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what is to be done?  The old way of doing things was to estimate the cost of a proposed project and compare it against the projected return (cost saving, ROI, new customers, whatever) in order to green light a project or not.  We &lt;em&gt;know&lt;/em&gt; the estimate is going to be off, in some  cases by an order of magnitude.  If we are honest we can also say that the projected return suffers from the same problem.  So I suggest dropping the whole thing and change how you green light projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Seed money:&lt;/strong&gt; Give a Product Owner (there should be one&amp;hellip;) some seed money and a team, maybe a month, maybe 3 depending on the product.  Get them to build something real, something representative of a final product.  Have a second round of funding meeting where Product Owners pitch for funding based on what they have built.  By that point they should have a much clearer picture of the real cost required (being 1% complete, 10% complete&amp;hellip;) to build a production ready product (including architectural signoff on plans, quality metrics on what has been built so far etc).  The return on investment should also be easier to quantify if not actually visualize with the working prototype.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Funding should be pretty ruthless at this point, it should be easy to scrap a product that is not showing enough promise in favour of something else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr/&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Notes&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;1&#34;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sydney_Opera_House&#34;&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sydney_Opera_House&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;2&#34;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_failed_and_overbudget_custom_software_projects&#34;&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_failed_and_overbudget_custom_software_projects&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
When I started looking at this I was reminded of something from another interest of mine, history.  Prior to Napoleon wars were relatively smaller affairs with troop numbers limited to around 30K due to economic constraints.  Napoleon was able to gather armies up to 300K-500K men funded a booming french economy.  The huge cost of the software projects listed here are far beyond the reach of most enterprises.  Much like war, mistakes at this scale can only really be funded by the economy of a large nation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;3&#34;&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/NHS_Connecting_for_Health&#34;&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/NHS_Connecting_for_Health&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;4&#34;&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Universal_Credit&#34;&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Universal_Credit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;5&#34;&gt;[5]&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Expeditionary_Combat_Support_System&#34;&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Expeditionary_Combat_Support_System&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;6&#34;&gt;[6]&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://web.mit.edu/curhan/www/docs/Articles/biases/67_J_Personality_and_Social_Psychology_366,_1994.pdf&#34;&gt;http://web.mit.edu/curhan/www/docs/Articles/biases/67_J_Personality_and_Social_Psychology_366,_1994.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Javascript Equality Operator Grids</title>
      <link>http://secretdeveloper.github.io/blog/2015/02/17/Javascript-Equality-Operator-Grids/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2015 12:52:32 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Gary Kenneally - @SecretDeveloper</author>
      <guid>http://secretdeveloper.github.io/blog/2015/02/17/Javascript-Equality-Operator-Grids/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Javascript gets some bad press these days especially over how its comparison operators work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided to extend &lt;a href=&#34;http://strilanc.com/visualization/2014/03/27/Better-JS-Equality-Table.html&#34;&gt;Craig Gidneys&lt;/a&gt; example and added ===, !=, !== &amp;lt;, &amp;lt;=, &amp;gt; and .= comparisons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rows are the left side operand and columns are the right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://jsfiddle.net/SecretDeveloper/1zywbpLL/&#34;&gt;Source code on jsfiddle&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://i.imgur.com/H9axhC3.png&#34; title=&#34;JS equality operator grids&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Directed Graph of hubski users created with D3</title>
      <link>http://secretdeveloper.github.io/blog/2014/12/16/Directed-Graph-of-hubski-users-created-with-D3/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2014 22:34:47 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Gary Kenneally - @SecretDeveloper</author>
      <guid>http://secretdeveloper.github.io/blog/2014/12/16/Directed-Graph-of-hubski-users-created-with-D3/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Using some c# code to scrape hubski.com I was able to produce a pretty basic directed graph showing users follower connections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/SecretDeveloper/SocialGraph&#34;&gt;Source code on github&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://secretdeveloper.github.io/items/hubski_graph.html&#34;&gt;Demo version&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://secretdeveloper.github.io/items/hubski_graph_advanced.html&#34;&gt;Advanced Demo version&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://secretdeveloper.github.io/items/hubski_graph.html&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://i.imgur.com/Ko6TQQ3.png&#34; title=&#34;Hubski Followers&#34; width=400 height=400 /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started off by scanning a users profile and recording various pieces of information such as:
- Age in days
- Number of followers
- Number of people followed
- Number of badges received.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I then looped over each of that users followers and recorded the same information,  and then their followers, and then their followers&amp;hellip;  you get the idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ended up thousands of accounts which was good but most of them only had 1 or 2 followers indicating a low level of social integration.  I filtered out most accounts with less than 25 followers (a few did make it in) in order to represent the core social group members.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I graphed the data using &lt;a href=&#34;http://d3js.org/&#34;&gt;D3&lt;/a&gt; into a force directed graph that included all of the connections (follows) between each of the gathered members.  There is some gravity applied to the area which results in the larger (more followed) users being drawn towards the center while the smaller users encircle them, like satellites basking in the glow of a shining sun, or hornets buzzing around fresh manure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s a work in progress, search needs to be fixed&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data Models, functional composition and validation</title>
      <link>http://secretdeveloper.github.io/blog/2013/08/06/Data-Models-functional-composition-and-validation/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Aug 2013 15:03:58 BST</pubDate>
      <author>Gary Kenneally - @SecretDeveloper</author>
      <guid>http://secretdeveloper.github.io/blog/2013/08/06/Data-Models-functional-composition-and-validation/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;While I am working my way through the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B00D624AQO/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;creativeASIN=B00D624AQO&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;tag=secretdeveloper-20&#34;&gt;Functional Javascript&lt;/a&gt; book I came across something that could be really useful, especially when dealing with AJAX requests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;toc_0&#34;&gt;Functional Composition&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a nutshell you start with simple functions that do a single job and then chain them up to perform some larger task.  In this example we want to validate that the json being returned from an AJAX call contains the properties we require.  To do that we start with the following function:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;function validator(message, fun){
    var f = function(){
        return fun.apply(fun, arguments);
    };
    f[&#39;message&#39;] = message;
    return f;
};
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;which takes a message string and a function as parameters and returns an object what can be called with an arbitrary number of arguments to perform a task.  The returned object has a &amp;lsquo;message&amp;rsquo; property assigned also.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next we need a &amp;lsquo;driver&amp;rsquo; function:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;function checker(){  
    var validators = _.toArray(arguments);  
    return function(obj){  
        return _.reduce(validators, function(errs, check){  
            if(check(obj))  
                return errs;  
            else  
                return _.chain(errs).push(check.message).value();  
        }, []);  
    };  
};  
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;that should be called with a list of validators as its arguments. It loads these into an array and returns a function which uses this array to validate the object &amp;lsquo;obj&amp;rsquo;. It will loop over each of the validators in the array and checks to see if the obj object passes each of them.  If the check fails then it appends the validators &amp;lsquo;message&amp;rsquo; to the list it will return. If all validators pass then the array returned will be empty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;toc_1&#34;&gt;Putting it all together&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can use my checker and validator functions to create a validation function like the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;function isValidResourceItem(){
    var validators = checker(

        validator(&#39;obj can not be nul&#39;,
            function(obj){return !_.isNull(obj);}),

        validator(&#39;obj must contain title&#39;,
            function(obj){return !_.isNull(obj.title);}),

        validator(&#39;obj must contain canonicalVolumeLink&#39;,
            function(obj){return !_.isNull(obj.canonicalVolumeLink);}),

        validator(&#39;obj must contain description&#39;,
            function(obj){return !_.isNull(obj.description);})
    );
    return validators;
};
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;which will help to ensure the data was returned in a format I expect and cut down on those &amp;lsquo;undefined&amp;rsquo; errors you would get without something like this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;toc_2&#34;&gt;Example&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I reused an example from an earlier jsFiddle to test the idea out, I want to be sure the search results json object contains the properties I need to produce a results list.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;100%&#34; height=&#34;300&#34; src=&#34;http://jsfiddle.net/SecretDeveloper/8PqEG/5/embedded/&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt; &lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;toc_3&#34;&gt;Whats the point?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well I guess it shows an easy way to take pieces of functionality, place them into small reusable functions and build upon them into a pretty powerful set of tools.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>KnockoutJS demo using Google Books API</title>
      <link>http://secretdeveloper.github.io/blog/2013/07/21/KnockoutJS-demo-using-Google-Books-API/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jul 2013 17:03:58 BST</pubDate>
      <author>Gary Kenneally - @SecretDeveloper</author>
      <guid>http://secretdeveloper.github.io/blog/2013/07/21/KnockoutJS-demo-using-Google-Books-API/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;toc_0&#34;&gt;Knockout.js&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_1&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A quick and dirty demo to show off a very simple example of what you can do with some knockoutjs code and an AJAX call.  I use the google books API to provide a simple search form.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_2&#34;&gt;Show me the Code&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;JSFiddle:
&lt;iframe width=&#34;100%&#34; height=&#34;400&#34; src=&#34;http://jsfiddle.net/SecretDeveloper/d9xfP/embedded/&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt; &lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out the &lt;a href=&#34;http://jsfiddle.net/SecretDeveloper/d9xfP/embedded/result/&#34;&gt;jsfiddle&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also use the &lt;a href=&#34;http://underscorejs.org/&#34;&gt;underscore&lt;/a&gt; library to work with the observableArray but that is not really a requirement.  I just like it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_3&#34;&gt;So whats happening?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We start off by creating a simple html page that contains a text box, a button and a results list. In our javascript file we create a ViewModel object (function) that contains properties that match our html form. It has a field for searchInput, a function to handle searches etc.  In our document ready function we apply this ViewModel to our html using &lt;code&gt;ko.applyBindings(vm);&lt;/code&gt;.  When we do this knockoutjs takes our html and resolves all the &lt;code&gt;data-bind=&amp;quot;&amp;quot;&lt;/code&gt; attributes we have added to elements and resolves them to fields on our ViewModel.  This is called Model Binding and it is a powerful tool that allows us to have a single ViewModel property displayed in several places on a page, with each kept in sync to any changes.  If the field we are binding to is a &lt;code&gt;ko.observable&lt;/code&gt; then any changes made to its value will immediately show wherever it is bound.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also use a &lt;code&gt;ko.observableArray&lt;/code&gt; to hold our search results.  When we initiate a search we make an AJAX call to the appropriate url and then parse the results.  You can see the result structure we receive back by running &lt;code&gt;curl -i https://www.googleapis.com/books/v1/volumes?q=potter&lt;/code&gt; (where &amp;lsquo;potter&amp;rsquo; is what you want to search for).  Once we receive the result we loop over the returned items and create a new resultItem to contain the information we want.  These items are then added to our array, &lt;code&gt;self.items.push(resultI);&lt;/code&gt; which thanks to knockoutjs gets rendered to our results div immediately.  You can see that knockoutjs can iterate over collections by using the &lt;code&gt;foreach:items&lt;/code&gt; databinding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_4&#34;&gt;Whats the big deal?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well this particular demo is about as easy as it gets, but even so it covers a few important topics:
    - &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Model_View_ViewModel&#34;&gt;Model View ViewModel&lt;/a&gt; pattern.
    - &lt;a href=&#34;http://knockoutjs.com/documentation/binding-context.html&#34;&gt;Model Binding&lt;/a&gt; as it applies to Knockout
    - Working with &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Web_API&#34;&gt;web API&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/a&gt; using &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/JSON&#34;&gt;JSON&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It shows what we can achieve with a few lines of code by building upon these powerful libraries.  KnockoutJS is taking care of binding our ViewModel to our html and also updates that html whenever we change an observable. jQuery is handling the AJAX request for us.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Functional javascript using underscore</title>
      <link>http://secretdeveloper.github.io/blog/2013/07/21/Functional-javascript-using-underscore/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jul 2013 15:03:58 BST</pubDate>
      <author>Gary Kenneally - @SecretDeveloper</author>
      <guid>http://secretdeveloper.github.io/blog/2013/07/21/Functional-javascript-using-underscore/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;toc_0&#34;&gt;Functional javascript using underscore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_1&#34;&gt;Why?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A little while ago I picked up &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B00D624AQO/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;creativeASIN=B00D624AQO&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;tag=secretdeveloper-20&#34;&gt;Functional Javascript&lt;/a&gt; by Michael Fogus.  I&amp;rsquo;m only part way through it and to be honest I should probably have waited until I finished it before starting this post but&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a central theme to this book which intrigued me, indeed its one of the main tenets of functional programming.  It can be summed up in this quote:
&amp;gt;&amp;ldquo;It is better to have 100 functions operate on one data structure than 10 functions on 10 data structures.&amp;rdquo; - Alan Perlis&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is very different concept to what is normally seen in large enterprise level projects and applications.  I have to say that I have spent a large amount of time writing code to map one model to another and back again. Its not fun. This functional stuff might be on to something.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_2&#34;&gt;What?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well Michaels book uses the &lt;a href=&#34;http://underscorejs.org&#34;&gt;underscore&lt;/a&gt; library for all of his examples and its a really powerful tool.  I have started using it here and there on smaller projects and the more I use it the more I like it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_3&#34;&gt;How?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://http://projecteuler.net/&#34;&gt;Project Euler&lt;/a&gt; is probably the go-to set of problems when developers try to learn a new language or framework.  I don&amp;rsquo;t see why I should be any different.  I have started a small project to play around with this and you can see it over on &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/SecretDeveloper/sdjs&#34;&gt;github&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;toc_4&#34;&gt;Problem 1&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we list all the natural numbers below 10 that are multiples of 3 or 5, we get 3, 5, 6 and 9. The sum of these multiples is 23. Find the sum of all the multiples of 3 or 5 below 1000.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Can be solved with a few lines of code like the following:
&lt;code&gt;
    return _.reduce(_.range(0,1000), function(memo, number){  
            if( number%3===0 || number%5==0) return memo+number;  
            return memo;}  
        );  
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;toc_5&#34;&gt;Testing&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unit testing javascript has come a long way in the last few years and I have added a simple QUnit test runner to the repository.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>