<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Javascript on My New Hugo Site</title>
    <link>http://example.org/categories/javascript/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Javascript on My New Hugo Site</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2015 12:52:32 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://example.org/categories/javascript/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Javascript Equality Operator Grids</title>
      <link>http://example.org/post/javascript-equality-operator-grids/javascript-equality-operator-grids/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2015 12:52:32 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/post/javascript-equality-operator-grids/javascript-equality-operator-grids/</guid>
      <description>Javascript gets some bad press these days especially over how its comparison operators work.
I decided to extend Craig Gidneys example and added ===, !=, !== &amp;lt;, &amp;lt;=, &amp;gt; and .= comparisons.
Rows are the left side operand and columns are the right.
Source code on jsfiddle</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Directed Graph of hubski users created with D3</title>
      <link>http://example.org/post/hubski-directed-graph-with-d3/hubski-directed-graph-with-d3/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2014 22:34:47 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/post/hubski-directed-graph-with-d3/hubski-directed-graph-with-d3/</guid>
      <description>Using some c# code to scrape hubski.com I was able to produce a pretty basic directed graph showing users follower connections.
Source code on github
Demo version
Advanced Demo version

I started off by scanning a users profile and recording various pieces of information such as: - Age in days - Number of followers - Number of people followed - Number of badges received.
I then looped over each of that users followers and recorded the same information, and then their followers, and then their followers&amp;hellip; you get the idea.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Functional javascript using underscore</title>
      <link>http://example.org/post/functional-javascript-using-underscore/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jul 2013 15:03:58 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/post/functional-javascript-using-underscore/</guid>
      <description>Functional javascript using underscore Why? A little while ago I picked up Functional Javascript by Michael Fogus. I&amp;rsquo;m only part way through it and to be honest I should probably have waited until I finished it before starting this post but&amp;hellip;
There is a central theme to this book which intrigued me, indeed its one of the main tenets of functional programming. It can be summed up in this quote: &amp;gt;&amp;ldquo;It is better to have 100 functions operate on one data structure than 10 functions on 10 data structures.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>