<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>Software - Category - SecretDeveloper</title>
        <link>https://secretdeveloper.github.io/categories/software/</link>
        <description>Software - Category - SecretDeveloper</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 12:00:00 &#43;0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://secretdeveloper.github.io/categories/software/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><item>
    <title>Building a Sudoku Editor with GPT-5.2</title>
    <link>https://secretdeveloper.github.io/blog/2026-02-06-building-a-sudoku-editor-with-gpt-5.2/</link>
    <pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 12:00:00 &#43;0000</pubDate><author>
        <name>Gary Kenneally</name>
    </author><guid>https://secretdeveloper.github.io/blog/2026-02-06-building-a-sudoku-editor-with-gpt-5.2/</guid>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>I wanted a Sudoku editor that feels like a quiet desk: place numbers, track candidates, get nudges, and keep the board readable. So I built one with GPT-5.2 helping me iterate the UI and logic.</p>
<p>You can try it here: <a href="/games/sudoku/" rel="">Sudoku Editor</a>.</p>
<h4 id="what-it-does" class="headerLink">
    <a href="#what-it-does" class="header-mark"></a>What it does</h4><ul>
<li>9x9 editor with keyboard navigation, input validation, and clear visual feedback.</li>
<li>Candidate mode with a manual pencil-mark layer, plus optional auto-candidates.</li>
<li>Generator with difficulty targets (easy/medium/hard) and uniqueness checks.</li>
<li>Step solver with hints and a log that explains the tactic used.</li>
<li>Quality-of-life actions: New, Reset, Undo, Copy, Load.</li>
</ul>
<h4 id="the-bits-i-like" class="headerLink">
    <a href="#the-bits-i-like" class="header-mark"></a>The bits I like</h4><ul>
<li>The board reacts quickly. It highlights row/column/box, matches values, and invalid cells without feeling noisy.</li>
<li>The candidate system has two layers: manual marks you place and auto-candidates the solver derives. You can flip between them without losing your notes.</li>
<li>The step solver does not just fill cells; it shows the reasoning and keeps a trail so you can walk back through the tactics.</li>
</ul>
<h4 id="how-the-solver-thinks" class="headerLink">
    <a href="#how-the-solver-thinks" class="header-mark"></a>How the solver thinks</h4><p>The solver starts with the basics (naked and hidden singles), then escalates through sets, pointing/claiming, fish, and wing tactics. I wanted the hints to be helpful rather than magical, so each step reports the evidence in plain language.</p>]]></description>
</item><item>
    <title>lsv: a Rust powered terminal file browser</title>
    <link>https://secretdeveloper.github.io/blog/2025-10-01-lsv-a-rust-powered-terminal-file-browser/</link>
    <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 12:45:00 &#43;0000</pubDate><author>
        <name>Gary Kenneally</name>
    </author><guid>https://secretdeveloper.github.io/blog/2025-10-01-lsv-a-rust-powered-terminal-file-browser/</guid>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>I finally snapped after one too many trips through modern file browsers on macOS and Windows. Click. Wait. Tiny target. Modal dialog. Repeat. I spend most of my day in a terminal anyway, so I built something that fits how I actually work.</p>
<p><img class="tw-inline" loading="lazy" src='/lsv.png'   alt="lsv"  ></p>
<p>Say hello to <a href="https://github.com/SecretDeveloper/lsv" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">lsv</a>.</p>
<ul>
<li>GitHub: <a href="https://github.com/SecretDeveloper/lsv" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://github.com/SecretDeveloper/lsv</a></li>
<li>Crates.io: <a href="https://crates.io/crates/lsv" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://crates.io/crates/lsv</a></li>
</ul>
<h2 id="what-i-wanted" class="headerLink">
    <a href="#what-i-wanted" class="header-mark"></a>What I wanted</h2><ul>
<li>Fly through directories with the keyboard</li>
<li>See a preview of the thing I have selected</li>
<li>Hit a key to run a command I chose</li>
<li>Keep the config in plain text so I can version it and move it across machines</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="what-lsv-is" class="headerLink">
    <a href="#what-lsv-is" class="header-mark"></a>What lsv is</h2><ul>
<li>A small terminal file browser written in Rust, scripted with Lua</li>
<li>Think of it like a fast directory lister that speaks key bindings and previews</li>
<li>Inspired by the excellent <code>lf</code>, but with a setup that matches how I like to glue tools together</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="why-rust-and-lua" class="headerLink">
    <a href="#why-rust-and-lua" class="header-mark"></a>Why Rust and Lua</h2><ul>
<li>I have been learning Rust for a few years and have built some small apps and tools with it, I like the language and it promises increased memory safety which is nice but the real reason is i like the tooling the language comes with, how it manages dependencies, and the cargo system along with crates.io for distribution.</li>
<li>Lua keeps the configuration simple and flexible without writing a plugin system</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="how-i-use-lsv" class="headerLink">
    <a href="#how-i-use-lsv" class="header-mark"></a>How I use lsv</h2><p>You can bind keys to run shell command. <code>e</code> for example might launch the selected file in your <code>$EDITOR</code> or i use <code>t</code> to launch a new tmux pane for the current directory, or <code>gs</code> which is bound to <code>lsv.os_run(&quot;git status -C {current_dir}&quot;)</code> to see the results in a results window.</p>]]></description>
</item><item>
    <title>Porting Asteroids to an ECS with Codex</title>
    <link>https://secretdeveloper.github.io/blog/2025-10-01-porting-asteroids-to-an-ecs-with-codex/</link>
    <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 12:00:00 &#43;0000</pubDate><author>
        <name>Gary Kenneally</name>
    </author><guid>https://secretdeveloper.github.io/blog/2025-10-01-porting-asteroids-to-an-ecs-with-codex/</guid>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Quick version: I rewired my <a href="/games/asteroids/" rel="">Asteroids</a> clone from a pile of classes to an Entity‑Component‑System (ECS). Codex (the CLI agent) did the heavy lifting while I poked, prodded, and occasionally muttered at my screen. The end result is cleaner, easier to extend, and less brittle when I add toys like missiles and sparkly shields.</p>
<p>Why bother with ECS?</p>
<ul>
<li>I was done fighting class hierarchies. I just want to slap “has a shield,” “spins,” or “is a missile” onto things without negotiating with a base class.</li>
<li>Data is data, behavior is behavior. Components hold state; systems do the work over sets of components.</li>
<li>(maybe) Performance as a side effect: tight loops over similar data are fast, but honestly the clarity is what sold me.</li>
<li>New features become “add a component, tweak a system,” not surgery across five files.</li>
</ul>
<p>Where I started (a.k.a. the creaky bits)</p>]]></description>
</item><item>
    <title>Using gpt-oss-20b to Build Asteroids and Breakout</title>
    <link>https://secretdeveloper.github.io/blog/2025-08-09-using-gpt-oss-20b-to-build-asteroids-and-breakout/</link>
    <pubDate>Sat, 09 Aug 2025 12:00:00 &#43;0000</pubDate><author>
        <name>Gary Kenneally</name>
    </author><guid>https://secretdeveloper.github.io/blog/2025-08-09-using-gpt-oss-20b-to-build-asteroids-and-breakout/</guid>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>In this post I explore how to use <strong>gpt-oss-20b</strong>, an open source 20-billion parameter language model, to prototype two classic browser games: Asteroids and Breakout. By iterating on prompts and refining the output, I generated working HTML5 Canvas implementations in around an hour or so.</p>
<h4 id="about-gpt-oss-20b" class="headerLink">
    <a href="#about-gpt-oss-20b" class="header-mark"></a>About gpt-oss-20b</h4><p>gpt-oss-20b is an open-source 20-billion parameter transformer-based language model released by OpenAI under the Apache 2.0 license. It is based on the GPT-4 architecture scaled to 20B parameters, trained on a diverse mix of web text, code, and documents.</p>]]></description>
</item><item>
    <title>Software Architecture</title>
    <link>https://secretdeveloper.github.io/blog/2018-10-05-software-architecture/</link>
    <pubDate>Fri, 05 Oct 2018 15:01:32 &#43;0100</pubDate><author>
        <name>Gary Kenneally</name>
    </author><guid>https://secretdeveloper.github.io/blog/2018-10-05-software-architecture/</guid>
    <description><![CDATA[<h1 id="what-is-software-architecture" class="headerLink">
    <a href="#what-is-software-architecture" class="header-mark"></a>What is software architecture?</h1><p>It depends. Everyone in IT asks this question at some point and the answer they get is a mixed bag depending on who tries to answer it. So to deepen the general state of confusion I thought I would add yet another definition.</p>
<h2 id="what-is-a-software-architect" class="headerLink">
    <a href="#what-is-a-software-architect" class="header-mark"></a>What IS a Software Architect?</h2><p>It depends.
I think of Software architects as “Master builders”. They may not have the title &ldquo;Architect&rdquo; but they are doing most of the following:</p>]]></description>
</item><item>
    <title>Software, Estimation and the Planning Fallacy</title>
    <link>https://secretdeveloper.github.io/blog/2016-10-14-software-estimation-and-the-planning-fallacy/</link>
    <pubDate>Fri, 14 Oct 2016 12:54:47 &#43;0000</pubDate><author>
        <name>Gary Kenneally</name>
    </author><guid>https://secretdeveloper.github.io/blog/2016-10-14-software-estimation-and-the-planning-fallacy/</guid>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>My flight is delayed for 3 hours so I&rsquo;m taking the rare opportunity to put together some thoughts on how software project estimation can trip companies, teams and individuals up.</p>
<h2 id="waterfall" class="headerLink">
    <a href="#waterfall" class="header-mark"></a>Waterfall</h2><p>Remember way back when everyone thought the Waterfall model was great?  Well actually no, for the most part they didnt. The Waterfall model was put forward by Winston Royce back in the early 70&rsquo;s as an example of a <em>broken</em> SDLC model.  Unfortunately this little note was lost in the scramble to adopt it as the de-facto model to use.  Now what is interesting to me is its original creator could see that the waterall model contained flaws, but thousands  of people could either not see those same flaws, or were unable to cease its adoption even if they tried; I&rsquo;m not sure which of those is worse.  30 years later you would be hard pressed to find any organizations still working under a Waterfall model, which is good.  The real problem however is not that a mistake was made, its that it took a generation before we acknowledged there was a problem.</p>]]></description>
</item></channel>
</rss>
