<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>Sudoku - Category - SecretDeveloper</title>
        <link>https://secretdeveloper.github.io/categories/sudoku/</link>
        <description>Sudoku - Category - SecretDeveloper</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2026 12:00:00 &#43;0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://secretdeveloper.github.io/categories/sudoku/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><item>
    <title>Building a Sudoku Editor with GPT-5.2</title>
    <link>https://secretdeveloper.github.io/blog/2026-02-05-building-a-sudoku-editor-with-gpt-5.2/</link>
    <pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2026 12:00:00 &#43;0000</pubDate><author>
        <name>Gary Kenneally</name>
    </author><guid>https://secretdeveloper.github.io/blog/2026-02-05-building-a-sudoku-editor-with-gpt-5.2/</guid>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>I wanted a Sudoku editor that feels like a quiet desk: place numbers, track candidates, get nudges, and keep the board readable. So I built one with GPT-5.2 helping me iterate the UI and logic.</p>
<p>You can try it here: <a href="/games/sudoku/" rel="">Sudoku Editor</a>.</p>
<h4 id="what-it-does" class="headerLink">
    <a href="#what-it-does" class="header-mark"></a>What it does</h4><ul>
<li>9x9 editor with keyboard navigation, input validation, and clear visual feedback.</li>
<li>Candidate mode with a manual pencil-mark layer, plus optional auto-candidates.</li>
<li>Generator with difficulty targets (easy/medium/hard) and uniqueness checks.</li>
<li>Step solver with hints and a log that explains the tactic used.</li>
<li>Quality-of-life actions: New, Reset, Undo, Copy, Load.</li>
</ul>
<h4 id="the-bits-i-like" class="headerLink">
    <a href="#the-bits-i-like" class="header-mark"></a>The bits I like</h4><ul>
<li>The board reacts quickly. It highlights row/column/box, matches values, and invalid cells without feeling noisy.</li>
<li>The candidate system has two layers: manual marks you place and auto-candidates the solver derives. You can flip between them without losing your notes.</li>
<li>The step solver does not just fill cells; it shows the reasoning and keeps a trail so you can walk back through the tactics.</li>
</ul>
<h4 id="how-the-solver-thinks" class="headerLink">
    <a href="#how-the-solver-thinks" class="header-mark"></a>How the solver thinks</h4><p>The solver starts with the basics (naked and hidden singles), then escalates through sets, pointing/claiming, fish, and wing tactics. I wanted the hints to be helpful rather than magical, so each step reports the evidence in plain language.</p>]]></description>
</item></channel>
</rss>
