<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Architecture on Another blog with random, unripenend thoughts.</title>
    <link>http://secretdeveloper.github.io/categories/architecture/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Architecture on Another blog with random, unripenend thoughts.</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 05 Oct 2018 15:01:32 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://secretdeveloper.github.io/categories/architecture/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Software Architecture</title>
      <link>http://secretdeveloper.github.io/post/softwarearchitecture/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Oct 2018 15:01:32 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://secretdeveloper.github.io/post/softwarearchitecture/</guid>
      <description>What is software architecture? It depends. Everyone in IT asks this question at some point and the answer they get is a mixed bag depending on who tries to answer it. So to deepen the general state of confusion I thought I would add yet another definition.
What IS a Software Architect? It depends. I think of Software architects as “Master builders”. They may not have the title &amp;ldquo;Architect&amp;rdquo; but they are doing most of the following:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On the Design of Small Things</title>
      <link>http://secretdeveloper.github.io/post/on-the-design-of-small-things/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Sep 2018 14:32:02 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://secretdeveloper.github.io/post/on-the-design-of-small-things/</guid>
      <description>Those who do not understand UNIX are condemned to reinvent it, poorly.
Henry Spencer
 The following is from the wikipedia article on Unix Philosophy. It is interesting to apply these rules when designing Microservices, there is significant overlap. Unix did it first.
In his book, The Art of Unix Programming that was first published in 2003, Eric S. Raymond, an American programmer and open source advocate, summarizes the Unix philosophy as KISS Principle of &amp;ldquo;Keep it Simple, Stupid.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>